Here we are fifteen years later and I still wouldn't change a thing.
This week a podcast listener asked me if I've changed my opinion on my top three exercises
for increasing the vertical jump.
And after thinking about it, no, I wouldn't change a thing.
Most of you have probably never seen these exercises before, but they're not new.
All of these clips are from 2011, yet I still think these are three of the most effective
special strength exercises for improving the vertical jump.
This first exercise is referred to as a powerbomb kettlebell swing.
It's still one of my favorite ways to develop violent hip extension due to the accelerated
eccentric portion of the lift.
Basically, a training partner throws the kettlebell down, which leads to a rapid descent.
And based on Newton's third law, we know that for every action there is an equal and
opposite reaction.
So the rapid descent leads to fast, powerful hip extension.
Next is a depth jump into an underhand med ball throw for height.
This exercise also accelerates the eccentric while teaching the athlete to absorb force
and immediately redirect it explosively, which is exactly what great jumpers do.
And finally, we have the dumbbell drop box jump, which is a phenomenal reactive power
exercise that teaches athletes to produce force quickly, all while minimizing ground
contact time.
It's basically a super set of a vertical jump holding dumbbells right into an unloaded box
jump.
So the loaded vertical jump potentiates the unloaded box jump, allowing you to produce
more force and jump higher.
So there you have it, three advanced exercises that have absolutely stood the test of time.
Hopefully you found this content informative.
And if you did follow me, I've been coaching for 30 years and got a lot of cool shit to
share.
Here we are.